wow you really have lowered your
expectations haven't you that's why I'm
so
happy I'm Angela Duckworth and I'm
Steven Dubner I'm a psychologist at Penn
and I run an educational nonprofit
called character lab you also wrote the
book grit yes and I am a writer and I
host a podcast called Freakonomics radio
and you wrote the book Freakonomics
among quite a few others I did and you
and I became friends we did and we
discovered that both of us really like
to ask each other questions and there's
only one rule the rule is there are Noid
questions today on no stupid questions
how do you know if you're a hard worker
you come up with a few Salient examples
right you think of your wife lazy no
she's not you think of me super lazy
andyw Duckworth never does anything also
why do happiness levels tend to start
dropping around age 16 and not rise
again until our late 40s to be precise
it's about 47 to 48 and I I only say
that cuz I'm 49 and so this matters lot
to
me Stephen I have a personal question
for you and I want you to be honest are
you a hard
worker I like that question because it's
first of all feels like a
trick second of all it is something I
think about a lot but I think about it
in terms of did I work as hard as I was
capable of working not like did I do a
lot okay so scale from 1 to 10
Steven DB am I a hard worker compared to
myself and my potential or compared to
like the universe of people let's go
with Universe of people so compared to
the universe of people I'm going to give
myself
8.7 so out of 100 people you would be
like harder working than 866 of them and
then yeah there's people in front of you
that I ridicule for working too hard the
other people Workaholics okay and then
what about compared to how hard you
could work I'm going to say 8.6
yes that's right yeah in other words I
feel like I could be you know in the top
10% maybe top 5% I could work harder but
I don't always push it as hard as I can
but I'm curious why you're asking this
question because you don't really care
about how hard I work well I'm asking
you in part because it's a question I
ask to measure grit being a hard worker
predicts success outcomes and I have
after 15 years of measuring whether
someone's a hard worker by asking them
are you a hard worker well does that
work asking them that question I
wouldn't think so well kind of you know
if somebody says yeah I'm absolutely a
hard worker then all things being equal
it is more likely that they're going to
achieve something then not there isn't
grotesque inflation there's certainly
possibility of Faking I mean remember
I'm a researcher so usually when I'm
asking people it's not because I'm
hiring them right so there's less of an
incentive to fake with somebody who's
you know not holding your future in
their hands but you still are like
holding a clipboard or some equivalent
thereof right you're an authority figure
well there's something else people do
that's not flat out faking and it it's
called social desirability bias we like
to appear in ways that are socially
desirable actually not only because we
think people with clipboards are
watching us or that anyone else is
watching us but turns out there's kind
of a form of social desirability bias
where you you don't want to look bad to
yourself people don't like to think
badly of themselves they just don't want
to reckon in the most honest way with
all their flaws and faults so there's
all kinds of reasons why we might
inflate our scores on something like on
a scale from 1 to 10 how hard a worker
are you now how much of this is what's
it called illusory superiority whatever
the lake wagon effect right oh yeah
optimistic bias right so how much of it
is a legitimate poor assessment because
we think we're better than we are a lot
of this does fall into that category
that at some subconscious level we just
don't want to think about ourselves in a
negative way we might actually think
we're being accurate but we're just
fooling ourselves CU we would like to
think that we're hard workers and how
much of this is about is it called
reference bias is that what your people
call this yeah I'm kind of obsessed with
this other reason why you know are you a
hard worker is not a perfect question
and that is the following can I just say
before you explain I love that your
question today is a question that you
think is prima fascia a bad question no
I do I'm serious it makes it more fun to
learn that the question was thought to
be poor but now you're going to tell us
why it's good that it's a poor question
yeah well at least I'll got to tell you
why it's interesting so when I ask you
are you a hard worker I think what
immediately comes to mind is like you
said compared to whom and you might say
like the universe of people in fact you
did but guess what Stephen you cannot
conter up the universe of people that
would be more than 7 billion right you
cannot imagine what the distribution of
humanity looks like and then Place
yourself somewhere in that distribution
what really you do is you come up with a
few Salient examples you think of your
wife lazy no she's not you think of me
super lazy Angie Duckworth never does
anything you're like you're like let me
revise my score
9.9 but you can see how these numbers
move around right and reference bias
refers to the bias of having a given
arbitrary frame of comparison that is
idiosyncratic and so you think you're
comparing yourself to the universe of
all people but you're not you're
comparing yourself to a very small
number of people and if you choose a
comparison set that happens to be super
hardworking then you're going to have
artificially lower responses one of my
favorite studies on this is
international study of Personality okay
and the personality trait that's being
studied is conscientiousness now some
countries one might argue are a little
more conscientious in general and I'm
not biased because of my Asian some
would say that the Far East that the
Chinese the Koreans and the Japanese on
questions like are you a hard worker are
you Dependable are you punctual are you
orderly that they might do better well
the least conscientious people in the
world by self-report are exactly those
people from the Far East and the authors
of the study said look it's
theoretically possible that all of our
stereotypes are 100% wrong but it's also
possible that these individuals from
these cultures have such high standards
for hard work and being orderly and the
trains running on time that they have
given them themselves lower answers is
asking about how hard you work a
particularly incisive or insightful
question if you want to measure
reference bias are you really going to
learn a lot about a person by how much
they may deviate from the norm by that
question I don't know that you know are
you a hard worker like how good it is on
its own but there is something you can
do with asking someone if they're a hard
worker and that is to give them little
vignettes little stories of other people
like this person wakes up at 5:00 in the
morning and then they start working at
7:00 and you can manipulate the heck out
of people well no it's not a
manipulation you ask them to then rate
the person in the story so you give them
series of stories and then you can tell
what their frame of reference is with
some Precision but you can kind of get
at whether this person is raiding hard
like are they a strict Raider or do they
have really lack standards because when
you give them a certain story you know
one person might say like yeah that
person sounds like a seven out of 10 and
another person might say slacker two out
of 10 so the are you a hard worker
question coupled with asking the person
to rate hypothetical others can get you
a little closer all right so let's say
take a room of a 100 people I randomize
them and for half of them I give them
examples of people who are demonstrably
hard workers this person gets up at for
da and the other ones I give stories
that are demonstrably not hard workers
then I have these two sets of 50 people
do a task do I see their assessment of
other people's hard work rub off in any
way and how well they perform ah so
you've designed an experiment where
you're kind of trying to Prime if you
will or like encourage hard work or not
hard work by giving them different
comparison sets right you know I'm not
not sure but I I am guessing that if you
give people examples of really hard
workers that if they feel like those
people you've described are similar to
them and the hard work is within their
grasp it's something they can do then
you'll get them to work harder but on
the contrary if you have given them kind
of Out Of Reach example like do you know
how hard Gandhi worked on this like let
me tell you how hard Gandhi worked on
this task they just lie down and take a
nap they just give up you know you've
held out these examples that actually
diminish their confidence that they
could do as well so reference bias it
can get complicated fast am I wrong to
think of it as essentially relativity it
is a kind of bias that comes out of
Relativity I actually think that
whenever anybody makes any kind of
statement like was it a good restaurant
how was the movie was it a good day that
actually there's always a frame of
reference I mean it doesn't mean
anything to say something without a
comparison and all reference bias is
saying is that times those frames of
comparison those references can be
different depending on the person and
that's why we get these kind of
paradoxical results was Albert Einstein
ever asked how hard a worker he was do
you think I wish he were I don't know
and I don't know what Albert Einstein
would say I will say he was actually
like a you know not so bad psychologist
so he might have had the psychological
insight to know that his standards of
hard work might be different than others
I love he was once asked to explain the
theory of relativity to someone who
didn't know or care about science at all
so this is what he reportedly said he
probably didn't say this but someone
says he want said he said well when you
sit with a nice girl for two hours you
think it's only a minute but when you
sit on a hot stove for a minute you
think it's two hours that's relativ i'
no way said that I don't know I will
tell you this in a book I'm reading
about Jewish history how Jews changed
the world it's said that five Jews
changed how we see the world most sign
ific l so Moses said the law is
everything and then Jesus said Love is
Everything Mark said money is everything
Freud said sex is everything and
Einstein said everything is
[Laughter]
relative still to come on no stupid
questions of course science says that we
can actually derive pleasure from
anticipated future rewards oh yeah the
vacation you haven't had yet is way
better than the one you just had always
[Applause]
[Music]
Angela Duckworth Steven Dubner here's my
question for you today it's about
happiness which is an interesting and
weirdly contentious subject in a way
because people disagree about what makes
happiness and you don't think about
happiness the way many people do many
people think of happiness is kind of you
know goal number one in life and your
father told you hell no I don't care if
you're happy be successful yeah I mostly
care about achievement as a psychologist
and as the daughter of my father but I
will tell you I grew up in the positive
psychology Center that's where I did my
PhD so you can ask me a happiness
question all right so different
disciplines look at happiness in
different ways different disciplines
call it different things but happiness
seems to be a word a lot of them have
landed on there's really three aspects
of happiness that are widely used one is
life satisfaction and then the second is
positive emotion like feeling energetic
or joyful now I know those sound like
the same thing but life satisfaction is
thinking that your life is good so
overall you would say oh I wouldn't want
to trade my life with anothers whereas
this kind of positive emotion thing is
quite literally feeling positively and
and those aren't exactly the same thing
but the third aspect of happiness is
actually very different and that is the
absence of negative emotions so the
absence of anxiety and depression worry
and so forth so anyway those are three
aspects economists tend to think about
life satisfaction more and there are
several economists who've been working
on this for many years David
blanchflower who's been one of The
Economist studying this recently
published a paper the latest and a long
line and he talks about the happiness
curve and if you look at the curve it's
a gigantic U like a smile and basically
it starts measuring happiness at age 16
and that's when people are the happiest
in these data at least and then it drops
and drops and drops and drops and then
it turns again at about age 50 yeah and
to be precise I think it's about 47 to
48 and I only say that cuz I'm 49 so
this matters a lot to me okay so you're
in for Good Times ahead so here's the
question if you believe the happiness
curve and that our happiness basically
drops from teenagerhood until kind of
whatever you want to call age 50 middle
age late middle age middle middle age
and then it swings really hard upward
for a long time if you do believe that
why do you think that is the case is it
that there are things happening in there
is it adjustments is it habituation
you're the olist tell us what so I've
seen this work by blanch flower and I
will tell you that it's very thorough I
think there's good reason to believe
it's real so generally what blanch
flower is using is survey data
self-report usually the phrasing is how
satisfied are you with your life I think
it may be because as you hit that
midlife period you're may be under a
combination of family stress cuz
parenting is not easy and work stress
and could it be that age 48 to 52 is
when many parents are seeing their
teenagers move out of the house that is
a possibility these samples don't only
include married adults but yes one of
the findings from Marriage research is
that you know so many married couples
with children fear the empty nest
syndrome but actually on average people
tend to be happier once they've sort of
gotten over the initial crying of your
last kid being dropped off to college I
think there are other explanations
though that's what I want to hear yeah
so blanch flower doesn't actually say
that he knows and I think that's right
to be humble about okay look there's
this u-shaped happiness curve but nobody
really knows for sure what's going on I
want to suggest that when you're in the
beginning of Life and this is what I
think might account for the downward
slope and happiness until you reach your
late 40s you are striving you are trying
to attain goals maybe that you're not
reaching and if you think about what
happiness is it's the achieving of the
goals that you set and there are two
ways to do that right one is to achieve
those goals and the other one is to have
lower goals so maybe the higher
expectations that we have for what we
hope for in life earlier that accounts
for why we're downward sloping until a
certain point and then we kind of reckon
with what's possible and then we're
happier can I ask you to unpack that a
tiny bit are you saying it's that
there's just less gap between kind of
our dream and reality or that we settle
that we habituate and become more accept
in of what we've got even if it wasn't
what we hoped it might be well that's a
pretty nuanced distinction but I I agree
there's kind of setting lower goals not
having high expectations for your life
and then alternatively there's keeping
those high expectations but having this
distanced perspective like very Zen
about the fact that you miss those goals
but I think either way what it says is
that the kind of increasing happiness
that you are predicted to experience in
your 50s and your 60s and so forth are
not because you're actually objectively
doing better but because in some way you
have subjectively changed the targets
themselves are you suggesting and I
think there is research that suggests
this that young people are
unrealistically optimistic and even if
the answer to that is yes can you really
say that it is unwisely because maybe
one of the things that you need a
surplus of when you're starting out is
optimism because in fact it can be hard
there is a psychologist who I love named
Don Moore he's like a judgment
decision-making scientist
and he believes that not only the young
but people of all ages can be recklessly
optimistic and he thinks that this
overconfidence is actually a problem I
mean when he says this entrepreneurs
just leap out of the woodwork and they
say you know you got to be optimistic to
get anything done and I think Don Moore
would say no it's just better to be
accurate and he has some experimental
evidence to support that I think that
these high aspirations that young people
have like rose tinted movies in their
head about what their wedding is going
to be like and how their children are
going to be beautiful and perfect and
all these projections into the future
which are probably a little naive I
think you could ask the question whether
they are really unwise or not I do think
that if you reach higher you'll get
farther but you might be less happy
doing it so let me ask you this since we
see that measured happiness is very high
at 16 and since you're talking about
Reckless optimism is a feature of that
age
how can you explain then the relatively
very high and increasing suicide rate or
maybe it does explain it maybe it's that
the cohort that are prone toward
Suicidal Thoughts are those who see that
gap between expectations in reality well
first of all I don't want to say that
optimism is inherently Reckless some
would say that it's Reckless I wouldn't
use exactly that language I might amend
your question to say look if young
people have these optimistic aspirations
we explained increasing rates of suicide
and depression and I think that's an
excellent question that's the question I
meant to ask I really don't think anyone
knows I mean I think the mystery of
increasing rates of anxiety depression
and suicide are still exactly that a
mystery one hypothesis that has been
Advanced is the same hypothesis that's
been Advanced for why a lot of other
people who are not just young adults or
adolescents are unhappy and that is that
we do have this ratcheting up of
expectations and so there is this Gap
gap between what we're achieving and our
aspirations not because we're achieving
less we're probably achieving more I
mean we're learning more we're having in
some cases higher quality experiences
but our aspirations are growing faster
than our objective achievements by the
way another possibility Stephen is that
the people who are happier are just
different from the people who are
depressed and they're both growing in
number and the middle is getting carved
out if you do believe these data
what do you do with it let's say you're
a 16year old person let's say you're
50-year-old person let's say you're a
75y old person by the way happiness does
start to decline when you're older a lot
of people around you are dying your own
health is not doing so well but if you
see that big u in front of you okay if
you're 16 or if you're in the middle of
the UPS slope how do you kind of hack
that happiness curve what do you do with
that information so let's start with the
16 R cuz I have one so what would I say
to one condolences oh she's so wonderful
she's actually a shockingly happy
16-year-old she's all over the data
that's right she's at the top of the
curve she just doesn't know what's ahead
also we should say the teenager can be
happy while making the parents miserable
yeah I think what teenagers experience
is actually like high highs and low lows
and there's a lot of scientific evidence
for that too I'm a university Professor
so I see lots of 18 to 22y olds who have
their fair share of enst and they kind
of are experiencing I think the decrease
in happiness they have memories of being
Carefree children and I think that
downward slope my guess is kind of
feeling the difference between what it
was and what it is today we're very
sensitive to changes and so to feel that
everything was so simple then and you
could eat an ice cream cone without
guilt and they're all of a sudden
burdened with the weighty
responsibilities of adulthood you know
their first career choices their first
disappointments professionally or maybe
major ones romantically when you're sad
it's just it's really hard to be
convinced that you'll ever not be sad so
I like to tell young people who are in
emotional turmoil or experiencing the
decrease in their emotional well-being
that life is long and that they won't
feel exactly this way forever well let's
say you're at the bottom right now right
technically you're about there so how do
you like exploit the oncoming you know
onslaught of Happiness you're about to
experience I mean other than just
looking forward which of course science
says that we can actually derive
pleasure from anticipated future rewards
yeah the vacation you haven't had yet is
way better than the one you just had
always right exactly so aside from
anticipating the future I mean this kind
of shift in your mindset from like oh
what's going to happen what could I do
what haven't I yet done to like life is
complicated and there's a lot to be
grateful for I know that blanchflower
and his colleagues do suggest that one
potential reason for the upswing in
happiness around midlife is that you've
seen people that you grew up with having
really bad fortune dying and whatnot as
you said your gratitude May kind of
start to kick in a little bit more I
mean the cynical interpretation of that
is is it's all downward social
comparison you look at people who like
oh my gosh I can't believe that happened
and that somehow makes you feel better I
mean just having some perspective right
and that is something that 16-year-olds
God bless them do not yet have an
abundance the wide angle lens on life
that allows you to appreciate a good cup
of coffee and wow nothing went wrong
today wow you really have lowered your
expectations haven't you I guess that's
why I'm so happy
so let me ask you one last question
let's say that someone listening to this
just wants to optimize their happiness
no matter how old they are no matter
what circumstances they're in one thing
that strikes me about looking at the
curve is it feels too imprecise to see
it grouped just by year of age right but
if I'm 52 and supposed to be at like the
bottom of my happiness about to climb
that doesn't really relate to the things
that actually happen dayto day so how
would you suggest people try to get rid
of the things that make them unhappy and
increase the ones that work anytime you
see a pretty graph that has like a nice
U or a line I mean you know it's an
average so it's not exactly the same
curve for everyone but I think more to
the point what can I do to actually make
my slope a little more steep or make my
inflection point happen now and not a
year from now I think the key to so much
of our emotional wellbeing is a tension
so for example if I think of what
happened in the last 24 hours I mean
gosh the mental landscape is vast
attention is Central because I can
choose to either think of all the things
that happened that were good or I can
choose to think about things that were
bad and if I make no choice at all the
default is to actually think of negative
things and that is why one of the most
reliable interventions to increase
happiness is called the three blessings
exercise and you simply think of three
good things that happened usually in the
last 24 hours and you rattle them off
I've gotten so good at it I can do it
usually in like 10 or 15 seconds you
know Lucy Amanda the avocado is ripe
wait just naming your children fulfills
the three that's what you're saying yeah
I know you're going to say that's like
kind of a cheat or how is that but yeah
when I bring my kids to mind I'm like
Lucy's healthy Amanda finished her
midterms and yeah I mentioned the
avocado I don't want to put that on the
same like level as my children but it
was a miracle of God that the avocado
was actually not too ripe and not under
and so yeah now just so you know that
avocado is probably grown in Mexico
where the avocado ranch is run by a
criminal cartel killing and extorting
innocent people I've got blood on my
hands but if that makes you happy Angela
that's fine there you go focusing on the
negative Steven you so much to
learn no stupid questions is part of the
Freakonomics radio network this episode
was produced by me Rebecca Lee Douglas
Stephen actually talks at greater length
about blood avocados in in last week's
episode episode 2 so check that out if
you haven't already and now here's a
fact check of today's conversations in
the first half of the episode Steven
references a quote about the theory of
relativity that's often attributed to
Einstein when you sit with a nice girl
for 2 hours you think it's only a minute
but when you sit on a hot stove for a
minute you think it's 2 hours that's
relativity Angela said that there was no
way that Einstein said that but a 1929
piece from The New York Times report
reports that when Einstein's secretary
was being bombarded with questions about
relativity Einstein shared this quick
little narrative as a way to communicate
the theory to interviewers the story is
more of an anecdote not a direct quote
but there are several versions of it in
circulation from the time period later
on in the episode step and Angela
discussed Reckless optimism and the work
of psychologist Don Moore Reckless is
probably too strong a word for how more
perceives optimism but he does conclude
that optimism doesn't improve
performance that doesn't mean that
pessimism is better Moore's experiments
found that pessimistic mindsets didn't
improve outcomes either instead like
Angela mentioned he says that realism is
the most desirable lens for achievement
that doesn't mean that optimism is never
beneficial meta analyses have shown that
it's linked to psychological well-being
and negatively correlated with
depression and anxiety so I guess stay
optimistic about life in general but
realistic when it comes to perform
performance goals I'm not super
optimistic that's realistic that's it
for the fact check and by the way Steven
and Angela usually drop lots of
references to books academic studies
specific researchers and we provide
links to all of them at freakonomics.com
nsq no stupid questions is produced by
Freakonomics radio and Stitcher our
staff includes Allison craiglow Greg
rippen James Foster and Karen Wallace
our theme song is and she was by Talking
Heads special thanks to David burn and
Warner Chapel Music if you'd like to
listen to our show ad free subscribe to
Stitcher premium you can also follow us
on Instagram and Twitter at nsq show and
on Facebook at nsq show thanks for
[Music]
[Applause]
listening I'm operating under the
premise that there's no such thing as a
stupid question I think that's an
excellent premise I could argue with
it Stitcher